How do big data systems handle massive datasets efficiently and
reliably? The secret often lies in something called an RDD.
Big Data processing needs fault tolerance and parallelization.
Traditional data structures struggle with this at scale.
An RDD, or Resilient Distributed Dataset, is a fundamental
data structure in frameworks like Apache Spark. Resilient means
it can rebuild lost partitions using its lineage. Distributed
means it's spread across many machines for parallel processing.
And Dataset refers to an immutable collection of elements.
Imagine filtering a huge log file. An RDD lets
you define transformations like 'map' or 'filter' on your
data, which are then executed lazily and in parallel.
RDDs are key to scalable, fault-tolerant Big Data
processing, enabling efficient parallel computation across clusters.