Ever wondered if a simple theoretical machine can
perform complex arithmetic? Today, we explore how a
Turing machine tackles subtraction, a fundamental operation.
A Turing machine works on an infinite tape with symbols,
using a head that reads, writes, and moves based on
its internal state. For subtraction, we'll represent numbers in unary
format, like three ones for the number three.
To subtract 'N' from 'M', we initially set up the tape with 'M'
ones, a separator, then 'N' ones. The machine then systematically 'crosses out' one
'1' from the minuend 'M' for every '1' in the subtrahend 'N'.
Let's visualize 5 minus 3. We have five ones, a separator, and
three ones. The machine would repeatedly mark a '1' from the first
group and a '1' from the second group until the second group
is depleted. The remaining ones are our answer: two.
This shows how even complex tasks like subtraction can
be reduced to basic symbolic manipulations, demonstrating the immense
power and universality of a Turing machine.