Circles are everywhere, from planets to pizzas! But
how do we describe their perfect symmetry mathematically?
Let's discover the equation of a circle.
A circle is all points equidistant from its center. We'll
use the distance formula: d equals the square root of
(x2 minus x1) squared plus (y2 minus y1) squared. This
connects directly to the Pythagorean theorem on a coordinate plane.
A circle is all points equidistant from a center (h, k). Any point
on the circle is (x, y), with a constant distance 'r', the radius.
Applying the distance formula, we get: the square root of (x-h) squared plus
(y-k) squared equals r. Squaring both sides reveals the standard equation of a
circle: (x-h) squared plus (y-k) squared equals r squared.
For a circle at (2, -3) with radius 5: (x-2) squared plus
(y-(-3)) squared equals 5 squared. This simplifies to (x-2) squared plus (y+3)
squared equals 25. See how the center and radius fit!
So, (x-h) squared plus (y-k) squared equals r squared beautifully
defines any circle, connecting its center (h,k) and radius 'r'
to its shape. A truly powerful and elegant equation!